Guide to the William C. Bouck papers, 1727-1866.
Bouck, William C. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
William C. Bouck papers, 1727-1866.
2206
Bouck, William C., 1786-1859.
2.6 cubic feet, 4 reels microfilm.
Correspondence, Memorabilia, Legal Documents, Printed Materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, appointment papers, official documents, and other papers chiefly relating to Bouck's political career.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Sheriff of Schoharie County, 1812-1814; member of the New York State Assembly, 1813-1814; Postmaster, West Middlebury, N.Y., 1821; member of the New York State Canal Commission, 1821-1840; Governor of New York State, 1843-1844; Assistant U.S. Treasurer at New York City, 1846-1849.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, appointment papers, official documents, and other papers chiefly relating to Bouck's political career include incoming letters concerning his duties as sheriff, the revision of regulations concerning the militia, and state and local politics. Also, considerable correspondence and reports on construction and repair of the Erie, Chemung, Chenango, Champlain, and Crooked Lake Canals, also information on technical problems, seasonal openings and closings, and labor procurement, 1830-1842; letters on political struggles over the enlargement of the canal, on internal improvements in general, on U.S. Mail contracts in Schoharie County, on his campaigns for the governorship in 1840 and 1842, and on the antirent movement in Scoharie and Rensselaer Counties. Correspondence as governor concerns appointments, reform of the judiciary, revision of state constitution, temperance, inspection of foodstuffs in Albany and New York City, Sabbath observances, conditions at state prisons with special attention to facilities for women, minors, and the insane, a Quaker's request for remission of fines under militia law, Candor residents' objections to the use of schools for religious meetings, sale of Oneida Indian Reservation land, state politics, the Barnburner-Hunker factionalism in the Democratic Party, and pre-Civil War tensions.
Later correspondence relates to Bouck's employment by the U.S. Treasury Department and to state and national politics. Other materials include deeds, bills of seizure, and other documents pertaining to the sale of lands in Schoharie County and adjacent areas. Additional items include New York State Militia commissions; copies of wills and probate papers, and other legal documents of Bouck, his father, Christian, and his grandfather William; papers relating to Bouck's Wisconsin land investments and his rental incomes and other personal and family business; estate inventory of Cornelius Feeck; and business papers of Benjamin and Juliet Best and John Ferguson. There are also papers regarding Bouck's activities in the Lutheran Church, including report on Hartwick Seminary property and correspondence on domestic and foreign missions. Miscellaneous items include letters on a portrait of Bouck by Charles Loring Elliott, a letter from John H. Bartholomew on conditions in Chicago in 1856, letters and advertisements on medical cures, and many pamphlets and reports. Correspondents include Daniel S. Dickinson, Lewis Cass, Samuel Beardsley, Jabez D. Hammond, Dorothea Dix, William L. Marcy, and others.
Includes a 1755 Royal land grant, with seal, from George II to William Bouck "confirmed a grant from the Indian occupants in 1747, [to] the property so long known as the Governor Bouck's farm, including Bouck Island" in the town of Fulton, Schoharie County, New York State. The farm was owned by the Bouck family until its sale in 1925 by Katherine Bouck Cornell and William Bouck Cornell to Edgar A. Church.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bouck, William C.,1786-1859.; Bartholomew, John H.; Beardsley, Samuel, 1790-1860.; Best, Benjamin.; Bouck family.; Bouck, Christian W.; Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866.; Church, Edgar A.; Cornell, Katherine Bouck.; Cornell, William B.(William Bouck), b. 1883.; Dickinson, Daniel S.(Daniel Stevens), 1800-1866.; Dix, Dorothea Lynde, 1802-1887.; Elliott, Charles Loring.; Feeck, Cornelius.; Hammond, Jabez D.; Marcy, William L.(William Learned), 1786-1857.; Democratic Party (N.Y.); New York (State).Legislature.Assembly.; New York (State).Governor (1843-1844: Bouck); New York (State).Militia.; United States.Dept. of the Treasury.
Subjects:
Sheriffs--New York (State)--Schoharie County.; Canals--New York (State); Postal service--New York (State)--Schoharie County.; Postmasters.; Elections--New York (State); Anti-rent War, N.Y., 1839-1846.; Temperance.; Food adulteration and inspection--New York (State); Sabbath legislation--New York (State); Prisons--New York (State); Women prisoners--New York (State); Quakers.; Conscientious objectors--New York (State); Church and state.; Indians of North America--New York (State)--Land tenure.; Indian reservations--New York (State); Lutheran Church--Missions.; Medicine, Popular.; Real property--New York (State); Real property--Wisconsin.; Public lands--Wisconsin.
Places:
Oneida Indian Reservation (N.Y.); Erie Canal (N.Y.); Chemung Canal (N.Y.); Chenango Canal (N.Y.); Champlain Canal (N.Y.); Crooked Lake Canal (N.Y.); New York (State)--Politics and government--19th century.; Chicago (Ill.)--Description and travel.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Alternate Form Available:
Materials from Accession 1 are also available on microfilm. Reel 1 consists of Political and Business Papers from 1771-1844 while Reel 2 covers 1845-1859. Reel 3 consists of New York State Canal Commission Papers from 1827-1851.
Other Finding Aids:
The original guide to the collection (a pdf file that uses bookmarks) contains additional information that might be useful to researchers, such as a list of correspondence related to Martin Van Buren.
RELATED MATERIALS
Schoharie County Historical Society. The Quarterly Bulletin. Apr. 1943: vol. 7, num. 2.
Hagan, Edward A. William C. Bouck: New York’s Farmer Governor. Westminster, MD: Heritage Books, 2006.
CONTAINER LIST
- A more detailed guide to the correspondence is available as a PDF file here: http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/EAD/pdf_guides/RMM02206.pdf
- Political and Business Papers (Accession 1), 1771-1859, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-37)
- New York State Canal Commission Papers, 1827-February 1835 (Box 1, Folder 38-43)
- New York State Canal Commission Papers, March 1835-1851, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-17)
- Political and Business Papers (Accession 2), 1798-March 1845 (Box 2, Folder 18-41)
- Political and Business Papers (Accession 2), April 1845-1859, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-25)
- Business and Family Papers, 1727-1866; Microfilm
- Business and Family Papers, 1747-1787; Photostats (Mapcase-folder 1)
- Royal land grant, with seal, from George II to William Bouck, 1755 (Mapcase-folder 1)
- Oversize Materials
  - Indenture between Joseph Bouck and John Gebhard, March 21, 1815 - March 17, 1823 (Mapcase-folder 3)
  - Newspaper clipping listing various laws passed in New York, several of which involve the canals, circa 1839 (Mapcase-folder 3)
  - Map of Milwaukee, 1840 (Mapcase-folder 3)
  - Report of the Commissary General on the state of the arsenal, March 29, 1842 (Mapcase-folder 2)
  - Bill for various goods, March 16, 1843 (Mapcase-folder 2)
  - Bill for envelopes, paper and similar goods, 1844 (Mapcase-folder 2)
  - By-laws of the National Life Insurance Company of the United States, circa 1849 (Mapcase-folder 2)
  - List of public property in Assistant Treasurer's office, 1849 (Mapcase-folder 2)